A story of two friends who didn't know they were supposed to be enemies.
The Fox and the Hound is a adventure, animation,
drama film directed by Richard Rich.
When a feisty little fox named Tod is adopted into a farm family, he quickly
becomes friends with a fun and adorable hound puppy named Copper.
Life is full of hilarious adventures until Copper is expected to take on his role as
a hunting dog -- and the object of his search is his best friend!
Tod (voice), played by Mickey Rooney.
Copper (voice), played by Kurt Russell.
Big Mama (voice), played by Pearl Bailey.
Amos Slade (voice), played by Jack Albertson.
Vixey (voice), played by Sandy Duncan.
Widow Tweed (voice), played by Jeanette Nolan.
The Fox and the Hound is a 1981 American animated buddy drama film produced by Walt Disney
Productions and loosely based on the 1967 novel of the same name by Daniel P.
It tells the story of the unlikely friendship between a red fox named Tod and a hound named Copper, as they
struggle against their emerging instincts and the realization that they are meant to be adversaries.
The film was directed by Ted Berman, Richard Rich, and Art Stevens.
It was produced by Ron Miller, Wolfgang Reitherman, and Art Stevens.
The ensemble voice cast consists of Mickey Rooney as Tod and Kurt Russell as Copper, respectively, with Pearl Bailey, Jack Albertson (in his final film role), Sandy Duncan, Jeanette
Nolan, Pat Buttram, John Fiedler, John McIntire, Dick Bakalyan, Paul Winchell, Keith Mitchell, and Corey Feldman providing the voices of the other characters of the film.
Mitchell and Feldman in particular voiced Young Tod and Young Copper.
The instrumental musical score to the film was composed and conducted by
Buddy Baker, with Walter Sheets performing the orchestration.
Walt Disney Productions first obtained the film rights to the novel by Daniel P.
Mannix in 1967; however, actual development on the
film would not occur until spring 1977.
It marked the last involvement of the remaining members of Disney's Nine
Old Men, which included Frank Thomas and Ollie Johnston.
Though they had involvement in early development of the film, it was ultimately handed over to
a new generation of animators following the retirement of the old animators.
As such, it was the first film for future directors,
including Tim Burton, Brad Bird, and John Lasseter.
During production, its release was delayed by over six months following the
abrupt departure of Don Bluth and his team of animators.
Further concerns were raised over the handling of the scene in which Chief is hit
by a train, which was originally planned to result in him dying.
After debating the handling of the scene, the filmmakers decided to change the
death into a non-fatal injury by which he merely suffers a broken leg.
The film was released to theaters on July 10, 1981, by Buena Vista Distribution.
It was a financial success, earning $39.9 million
domestically and receiving mixed reviews from critics.
It was nominated for three awards, of which it won one.
At the time of its release, it was the most expensive animated
film produced to date, costing $12 million.
It was re-released to theaters on March 25, 1988.
An intermediate follow-up, The Fox and the Hound 2, was
released directly-to-DVD on December 12, 2006.
The film explores themes of friendship, based on
novel or book, fox, coming of age, dog.
The tone is lighthearted and emotional.